[SPEAKER_00]: I'm intrigued by the philosophy of Buddhism, but I seem to disagree with the goal.
[SPEAKER_00]: I am not afraid of suffering, and I find that adversity is what makes me a better person, is what drives society to improve, and gives meaning to human life.
[SPEAKER_00]: My first impression is that trying to simply get rid of suffering is a sign of weakness and fear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But on the other hand, to me, the life of a monk seems quite difficult, and far from this notion of comfortable escapism.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not so sure what to think, and your clarification here would be appreciated.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it certainly is a weakness to try to get rid of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's the wrong path.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's ironically what most people are trying to do through what they think Buddhism is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, everybody could recognize escapism as kind of short-term benefit, long-term harm.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's pretty obvious.
[SPEAKER_01]: And what you would be doing, if you're practicing rightly, is actually exposing yourself to suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not in a blind, sort of, for-its-own-sake kind of way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather, you would be doing things that naturally result in suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not because you want the suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Rather, restraint, renunciation, taming your desires, brings up suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the opposite of what you've been cultivating.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a path that is thorny because you've let it get over ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so... it actually... you don't have to... you don't have to be afraid that you'll be escaping or running away from stuff if you start practicing the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's a reason why people don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's because...
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else that they're doing is because they're running away from this.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're running away from the the wild mind that comes up when you just go into seclusion, for example.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is not really what you should start with, because you would probably go mad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you would... if you take it on all at once, you take the average person and you put them in a solitary confinement,
[SPEAKER_01]: They will realize that everything else was actually a coping mechanism for this stuff that they start to experience when they're withdrawn from all their distractions.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is difficult only because, like I said, you have been getting used to the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you learn how to... well, if you... you could say if you just do it long enough, but also it's not about just blindly doing it and waiting for some result.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you learn how to develop the right values,
[SPEAKER_01]: Without impatience, without trying to force your mind to delight in the opposite and give up everything and just be free from craving and all that, you realize where
[SPEAKER_01]: The line of your input is, as the simile of the Buddha, the Buddha used for taming a wild elephant, you don't just, like, set this goal of tomorrow I'll have it following all my commands perfectly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You realize that there's this... all these habits and all these things that have been built up because that elephant has been just living in the wilderness for the last 30 years.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to have patience to see, oh, yeah, it will have to be painful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it will have to be kicking and screaming, but then, that can't last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, and certainly, if you were to quit, and if you were to just give up on the whole thing, and say, oh, I'll just let the elephant go back in the wilderness, well, it's not like you can actually...
[SPEAKER_01]: The simile doesn't go so far in the sense that
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, an elephant, you just go let it go and fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not your problem anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you will have to face the consequences of not having tamed your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: In fact, well, you're already facing them, whether you like it or not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you would see that just the fact of certain things causing you suffering or being able to cause you suffering already has an impact here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already in defense stance, so to speak, even if you're not actively fighting them.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that whole apprehension that everybody has towards sickness, aging, death, their dear things being taken away, which is happening again, pretty much all day long.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, if they were to recognize that's the state of defense that they're in,
[SPEAKER_01]: They will realize, oh, if I don't do anything about this, it's not actually... it's not like I... like I'm actually avoiding all this difficulty of the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm actually exposing myself to a difficulty that is worse, because it has no end.
[SPEAKER_01]: That difficulty has no day.
[SPEAKER_01]: The difficulty of being subject to suffering, still being... having attachments and being liable to craving,
[SPEAKER_01]: A difficulty will never disappear on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas the practice, even if it takes you 50 years to even feel like you know what you're doing with a dhamma, it can't last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the difficulty can't last forever.
[SPEAKER_01]: At some point, those strong defilements that you started with will have to get weaker.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you start to see, oh, this is actually working.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then the whole thing becomes a bit more bearable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, either way, not doing the practice will always be worse, will always bring more suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if the suffering of the practice is more acute, feels like it's more concentrated, the suffering of not practicing might feel like it comes and goes, but it has no end.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's much worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe an extension of the simile of the elephant could be the reason that you brought it in to be tamed in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not so much because you want to have a royal elephant, but there was an elephant that would from time to time come and attack your village.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And most of the time it wasn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: But sometimes, it would.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the fact that it might was enough to make you go out and go through this.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, that would be a better... Because, yeah, it's not like I'm just chasing this reward for the sake of its own pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like if I don't get it, I will have to face the consequences.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not just I didn't get what I wanted.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's I will be actively exposed to what I don't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: Pain, like suffering, lamentation, sorrow, despair.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's either you abandon those things and develop yourself, or you accept that you're going to be exposed to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's no middle ground.
[SPEAKER_01]: What might seem like a middle ground is managing your circumstances, but that is not a middle ground at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's really just postponing, having to face the sorrow, lamentation and despair.
[SPEAKER_01]: Postponing it in a way that usually makes it painful, even more painful when you have to face it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you were...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's kind of like when you really build up this sense of anticipation,
[SPEAKER_01]: For some unpleasant thing that you have to face, rather than just facing it right away, it usually makes it worse, usually makes it more of a... that sense of fear builds up even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the management actually isn't the middle way between practicing and not practicing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's still very much within the not practicing side.
[SPEAKER_01]: And we'll have you facing the consequences sooner or later.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because another thing as well is, you don't know how well your management will... how well you'll be able to maintain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it depends on all of these external conditions that could just like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: Whatever, climate change, war, anything could just compromise your ability to keep all these pains and all these displeasures at bay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it it requires a very very big leap of faith to think that you can just kind of live your whole life, kind of just
[SPEAKER_01]: Keeping your head above the water, just managing the conditions, doing what you can to prevent bad things whenever they come up or to ameliorate them, takes a big leap of faith to see that as a good option.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like hanging from a thread perpetually.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your state is just hanging from this thread that you have no idea when it will break.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you would never accept that deal if you had a choice.